The Great Work of Your Life by Steven
Cop. Quote, "People actually feel
happiest and most fulfilled when meeting
the challenges of their dharma in the
world. When bringing highly concentrated
effort to some compelling activity for
which they have a true
calling." Hi and welcome to the book
lab. I'm Bj and in today's video we're
going to talk about Steven Copes the
great work of your life. This book is
about finding your life's work, your
dharma, your vocation, your calling. And
in this review, I'm going to share some
key concepts from this book as well as
sharing some anecdotes from my own life
and how I've taken step towards my own
calling and my own great work. The book
is highly inspired by the Bhagavad Gita.
This is an ancient um Hindu scripture
that has inspired people across the
world for ages. It's a very important
book. It's not an ordinary book. It's a
book that have given spiritual nurture
to so many people and many prominent
figures as well such as the thorough
Gandhi Openenheimimer just to name a
few. It's also a cornerstone piece in
the yogic tradition. A book that I urge
everyone to read. I've read it a few
times myself and I'm going to keep doing
it. This book takes um inspiration from
the Gita and brings it into context by
telling stories about famous people that
found their dharma as well as regular
people who took steps towards their
life's work. So it's a mix of both. So
what is dharma in this context? It's a
work activity that aligns with who you
are that uses your unique abilities.
This is the type of work that doesn't
feel like work to you. It could be that
you love to help people so you become a
nurse or you master your skill and
become the best juggler in the world. Or
maybe you want to take on society as a
whole and move it in another direction.
But the problem is it's hard to find
your dharma. So how do you go about
finding it? The book provides a few
ideas around this. This is the tricky
part. Where do I look for it? Oftenimes
hints about your dharma can be found in
childhood fascinations
uh your traumas or your fears. My own
first step towards my dharma was when I
became fed up with my deadend job as a
store clerk filling up uh grocery
shelves day in and day out and I just
had it at one point. Um so I knew I
really needed to quit. I needed to get
out of there but where would I go? So I
look back in the past and trying to find
what I actually had a natural curiosity
about and what was fun to me. And I
remember back in school at one point we
had when I had a multimedia class that I
was studying, we had something called
virtual environments where we built this
big g video game level of our school.
And that work that 3D work in creating
that virtual environment was one of the
most fun projects that I ever partaken
in. and I didn't want to go home when
the school bell rang. So there was my
hint. I was going to be a game
developer. I had no pre prior skills or
anything. I had no idea how to become
one. But following that lead, I
eventually made it there through many
hard years of work. But still I followed
that trail and I ended up spending 15
years working in this field that really
fascinated me that was a source of um
flow uh and very fulfilling work in
general. Fear could also be an indicator
of dharma for me. I've always wanted to
be able to share my ideas with other
people and maybe publicly even. The
problem is that I've been scared
shitless to stand in front of a crowd or
be at the center of attention in any
way. I shied away from that and at some
point I realized this was problematic
for me. This was an obstacle then that I
needed to overcome and that became
obvious when I felt like I wanted to
share what I've learned from books what
I do here on the book club and I really
was not able to do it. So I signed up
for a course for something called Toast
Masters where you can practice public
speaking through doing several speeches
in front of people in the club over and
over and over again. And through that
process uh it was really hard and
stressful for me. But at some point the
fear started to uh become subdued and I
was able to start this channel. You see
the point here? The fear is trying to
tell you something. It tries to tell you
that something is important to you and
that you need to address whatever is
stopping you. Quote, "What you fear is
an indication of what you seek." Trauma.
Trauma could be another guidepost on
your path to dharma. What happened to
you that allows you to in a unique way
help others avoid ending up in the same
place or to help them heal. There's a
lot of energy bound up in trauma and if
you can find a way to sh challenge it,
channel it in in a good and positive
way, there's a lot of meaning that can
come from that. Quote, if we live
another person's or a dharma that is
false to us, at some point we wake up to
the fact that the only person who truly
care what we do with our lives is you.
Okay. So the book talks about the search
for dharma but what to do when you find
it. When you find it you have to lean in
and
commit. But we also have to recognize
that dharma is not a destination but a
journey. Sometimes dharma runs its
course like when game development no
longer fulfilled me in the same way and
something else something new came into
view like lifelong learning and
understanding for instance. Transition
is hard. You're at a crossroads and
that's when metaphorically you need to
sit down in your folding chair and
listen what is right for me and many
people get stuck at this crossroads and
never take the next step. You never have
perfect information. You can't wait
until you're 100% certain before you
start the next thing. That's important.
Life is short. Remember, try things,
pick a path, and be ready to pivot. And
when you do commit, commit fully. Clear
away distractions. Simplify everything
and aim everything towards that
meaningful activity. Say no to what
doesn't align with your dharma. Go
allin. This part of the book was
fantastic. The part about committing to
your dharma. And this is where we got
some really good stories, especially the
examples of Robert Frost and Toro and
how they fully committed to their
dharma. Quote, boldness has magic in it.
Whatever you can do or dream, you can do
begin it. And on Frost, the author says,
quote, his dharma required him to farm,
so he bought one. His dharma required
him to give up teaching, so he did.
Another favorite part of this book is
the story about Gandhi and how he fully
committed to his mission. He simplified,
he unified, he aligned his life in
accordance with his dharma. And I really
want to recommend a book thinking about
that. Okay. Okay. Yeah. This is uh the
story of my experiments with the truth
by Mahatma Gandhi. Um, I really love
this book because
it tells the story uh straight from the
horse's mouth how Gandhi experimented
with this and that on his way to finding
his calling in the world and it's is
fascinating following his uh process
especially knowing uh where he would end
up later on and then there's Beethoven
who continued to compose uh even though
he was going death and he was going at
it like a mad hound
So these are the type of stories that
you will hear uh from this book. H some
are more interesting than others
depending on your taste. Of course,
there's some stories about some doctors
or whatever that didn't really grab me.
But but hearing about Gandhi and
Beethoven and these more extremely
committed people that was really and
truly inspiring for me and I I just know
that I need to read a biography about
Beethoven that's u on my reading list.
Let me know if you have any
recommendations uh on that topic. Now,
let's jump into the book verdict. And by
the way, if you enjoy the content of
this channel or if you've gotten some
value out of out of this channel, picked
up a book or whatever, then you can
support me back by giving a thumbs up,
subscribe. It really helps me reach more
people with these great books that we
talk about here on the channel. I found
the great work of my life being a great
book for
refocusing. It makes you ask, am I
spending my energy in the right way? Am
I fully expressing my curiosity,
creativity, and my unique uh
contributions to the world? And my
favorite lesson, it's of course from the
Gita, and it's about outcome
independence when you commit till
whatever your calling is. Quote, let go
of the fruits of your action. You have
the right to work, but never to the
fruit of work. A slippery but beautiful
idea. We are told never act for the sake
of a reward but also don't avoid action.
Perform your work rooted in your deeper
self. Calm in both success and failure.
So it's a book I recommend and I can
recommend this book right away. The
Bhagavad Gita as well. It is a fantastic
book that I keep reading over and over
again. This is a great introduction to
the Bhagavad Gita and when it comes to
what you're supposed to do in your life,
it's a great book for anyone feeling a
bit stuck maybe in doing a dead-end job
and wanted to find a path forward. It's
an enjoyable book. It's a book club
recommendation. Next week, I'm back with
more book reviews. I've just finished
the big print and who knows maybe it
holds the secrets to why prices go up,
why we all struggle to be able to afford
a home. What is the root cause of this
problem and what is the solution? So,
tune in to that review. It will pop up
in the channel quite soon, I hope. And
also, we have the June releases, the
most interesting non-fiction releases
that are coming out in June. That video
is either live right now or will be
published very soon. I'm going to record
it right after this. Happy reading
everyone. See you next week. Be out.